Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
JW Broadcastingにようこそ！
Here’s what we
can look forward to in our program:
今月のプログラムでは
次の点を考えます
What if your courtship
reveals problems you didn’t expect?
交際期間中に予期しなかった問題が
明らかになったならどうしますか？
Part 3 of the Preparing for Marriage series
“結婚に備える”シリーズの
パート3では—
will show us how we
can “calculate the expense”
結婚を考える際にどのように
“費用を計算”できるかが示されます
when considering marriage.
We go to Australia
to meet Viv and Ann Mouritz.
オーストラリアでビブ・モリッツと
妻のアンに会います
Their life of full-time service
has taken them around the world.
お二人は世界中で
全時間奉仕を行なってきました
What advice do they have
for those who are deciding
神聖な奉仕を追い求めている人たちは—
what form
of sacred service to pursue?
お二人からどんなアドバイスを
聞けるでしょうか？
このプログラムの
主題を強調する—
And we’ll enjoy
a music video that highlights
ミュージック・ビデオも
楽しめるでしょう
the theme of our program.
It will encourage us to settle differences
with our brothers and sisters
兄弟姉妹との不和を解決し
互いに許し合うよう強められます
and to forgive one another.
では2016年10月の
JW Broadcastingです!
This is the October 2016 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
We begin with a report from Ukraine.
まず ウクライナからの報告です
In 2014,
political tensions in eastern Ukraine
2014年 ウクライナ北部で
政治的な緊張が高まり—
boiled over
into a full-blown military conflict.
軍事紛争へと発展しました
Within months,
数か月以内に7,600人以上の
エホバの証人が—
over 7,600 Witnesses
避難所を求めて
逃れる必要が生じました
needed to flee the area
to seek refuge.
Others sheltered in their homes.
自宅に隠れていた人たちもいます
How did our brothers
survive physically
兄弟たちは身体的にも霊的にも
どのように生き延びたのでしょうか？
and spiritually
through the fighting?
Relief was organized
from hundreds of miles away
数百キロ離れたリボフにある支部で
救援活動が組織されました
at the branch office in L’viv.
In the following interviews,
次のインタビューの中で—
兄弟姉妹たちは組織や互いから受けた
愛と世話について述べています
our brothers and sisters
describe the love and care
they received from the organization
and from each other.
何の予告もなく 戦いが始まりました
It happened that the hostilities
started without warning,
兄弟たちはすぐに逃げなければ
なりませんでした
and the brothers needed to flee quickly.
There was not enough food;
十分な食べ物はなく
店にも何もありませんでした
there was nothing in the stores;
there was a lack of medicine;
薬も不足し
水も電気もありませんでした
there was no water,
no electricity.
It was scary.
怖ろしかったです
There was no stability at all.
非常に混乱していました
We did not know what to do.
どうすれば良いか
わかりませんでした
留まるべきか？
それとも 逃げるべきか？
Should we stay, or should we leave?
There were triplets;
they were seven years old.
7歳になる 三つ子の
子どもたちがいて—
As soon as they
got into the shelter,
シェルターに入るとすぐ
王国の歌を歌い始めました
they started singing
a Kingdom song.
The adults
also joined them in singing,
大人もその歌に加わりました
and because of that,
we couldn’t hear the explosions
おかげで外の爆音が
気になりませんでした
that were happening outside.
True, we ran out of foodstuffs,
食料は尽き
お金もありませんでしたが—
and we had no money.
切り抜けられると信じていました
But I knew we would be able to get by.
神がわたしたちを飢え死に
させることはないからです
God would not let us die of hunger.
Because the shelling was happening
so often, it was impossible
撃ち合いや爆発が頻発していたので
通常の集会は開けませんでした
to conduct our usual meetings.
We also couldn’t organize the ministry
in the normal way.
普段のような宣教を
組織することもできませんでした
It was just too dangerous.
あまりにも危険だったからです
When we received the first reports
about the unrest in the east,
東部での紛争に関する
最初の報告を受けると—
our Branch Committee gathered
支部委員会は集まって
祈りのうちに状況を分析しました
and we prayerfully analyzed
the situation.
兄弟たちを 霊的また身体的に
守るため—
We asked Jehovah for wisdom
—how to act,
どのように助けられるか
エホバの知恵を求めました
how to help our brothers
to be spiritually and physically safe.
統治体にも
最新の報告を送り続けました
We were also sending regular
update reports to the Governing Body.
More than 156 tons of food
会衆から 156トンの食料と
21トンの衣服が寄せられ—
and 21 tons of clothing donated
仲間の兄弟たちに そして—
by local brothers have been distributed
エホバの証人以外の人々にも
分配されました
to fellow believers
and also to some non-Witnesses.
We had been told
that we would be receiving
最初は 5トンの救援物資を
受け取ると聞いていました
about five tons of relief supplies.
それで 5トンではなく 実際には
15トンを受け取ったときは—
So we were astounded
when instead of 5 tons,
本当にびっくりしました
we received 15 tons!
It was lovely to find little notes
箱の中には 兄弟姉妹たちの書いた
メモも入っていて 嬉しかったです
that our brothers
and sisters had written
and included in the packages.
Brothers from neighboring cities responded
近くの都市の兄弟たちは 家を提供し
食料を備えてくれただけでなく—
and offered their homes,
provided foodstuffs
何よりも 兄弟として
温かく迎え入れてくれました
and, more importantly,
their brotherly hospitality.
So we are ready to make sacrifices,
兄弟たちを助けるため
犠牲を払い—
to adjust our schedules,
予定を調整し 家族の時間の幾らかさえ
用いる覚悟でいました
and to even take time
out from our families
to render practical help
to our brothers.
For example,
beginning at 6 a.m.,
兄弟姉妹が必要とするものを届けるため
朝の6時に出かけました
I would visit
the brothers and sisters
and bring them
the things that they needed.
So during two and a half months of war
紛争のあった2か月半と
復旧のための2か月の間に—
and two months of reconstruction,
I rode my bicycle
自転車で6,500キロ 走りました
6,500 kilometers.
スラバンスクの長老たちは
小さな会衆を組織し—
The local elders from Slavyansk
organized small congregations
兄弟たちを霊的に支えるため
定期的に集会を開きました
and regularly conducted meetings
to support them spiritually.
Major repairs
have been carried out on 20 houses
兄弟姉妹の家屋
20棟で大規模な修繕が—
of brothers and sisters,
and minor repair work
72の家屋で小規模な修繕が
行なわれました
was done on 72 houses
and apartments.
We prepared two more programs.
二つのプログラムが
準備されました
This time, not only
for the congregations in the war zone
紛争地域だけでなく
ウクライナ全域—
but for the whole country of Ukraine,
そしてロシアやベラルーシの
会衆も加わりました
even for Russia and Belarus.
We even had 325,000
in attendance.
出席者は
32万5千人に及びました
興味深いのは
エホバの証人ではない人々の反応です
An interesting experience
was the response of the people
who were not Jehovah’s Witnesses.
それぞれ自分の宗教がありますが
こう言うんです
They belong to another religion,
yet they said:
“皆さんだけが
本当に気遣いを示し—”
“You are the only ones
that really care.
“行ないによって
純粋な愛を表わしています”
Your genuine love
is shown by your deeds.”
This is what makes us different
これこそが
他の宗教との違いです
from all other religions.
This unselfish love
shown by our brothers
主人も息子も—
兄弟たちが利他的な愛を
示していることに気づきました
did not go unnoticed
by my husband and my son.
主人は聖書研究を始め
今では定期的に集会に出席しています
My husband
started studying the Bible,
and he regularly attends
the meetings now.
Recently, he enrolled
in the Theocratic Ministry School.
最近 神権宣教学校にも
入校しました
わたしはこの愛を
個人として経験して—
I experienced this love personally,
and I started studying
the Bible again with the brothers.
兄弟との聖書研究を再開しました
今 バプテスマに向けた
準備をしています
Now I am preparing for baptism.
Unfortunately,
one of our sisters was killed.
残念なことに
一人の姉妹が命を落としました
I realized that a person can lose
人は すべての物を失うことが
ありますが—
—lose everything, but that
自分の子供を失うことに比べれば
大したことではありません
is really nothing
compared to losing your children.
兄弟姉妹は わたしたちに
耳を傾け—
The brothers and sisters listened to us.
We cried together.
共に泣いてくれました
I just can’t put it into words.
言葉にできないほど
嬉しかったです
It is as if Jehovah
is holding you in his arms
まるでエホバの腕に
抱かれているかのようでした
—he doesn’t let you fall—
神は わたしたちが
倒れるままにはされず—
as if he is saying to you:
“愛する者よ 手を離さないで”
‘Don’t let go, my dear one.
“わたしがあなたを助け 支える”
と言っておられます
I’m helping you.
I’m supporting you.’
With Jehovah there are no borders
between nations.
エホバの民の間に
国境はありません
I could see
that this was the true religion.
これこそ 真の宗教です
We continue to pray
for our brothers in Ukraine.
ウクライナの兄弟たちのために
引き続き祈りましょう
わたしたちはエホバの愛を
確信していますし—
We’re confident
of Jehovah’s love for them,
エホバはどんな試練においても
兄弟たちを支えてくださることでしょう
and we know he’ll sustain them
through any tribulation.
Our worldwide brotherhood
is truly special.
わたしたちの世界的な兄弟関係は
実に特別なものです
When our brothers are in need,
兄弟たちが困っているとき
何でも助けになりたいと願います
we want to help
in whatever way possible.
It also brings us great joy
to be with our brothers
また集会 野外奉仕
その他どんな時でも—
—whether at the meetings,
in the field service,
兄弟たちと共にいることを
大きな喜びと感じます
or on other occasions.
We love our brothers
and enjoy spending time with them.
兄弟たちを愛しており
一緒に時を過ごすのは喜びです
At the same time,
because we are all imperfect,
とはいえ わたしたちは不完全ですから
愛と一致が試みられることもあります
our love and unity will be tested.
We may have our feelings hurt,
感情を傷つけられたり
傷つけたりすることがあります
or we may hurt
the feelings of others.
That brings me to the theme
I would like to discuss
それで今月のプログラムでは—
with you
in this month’s program,
“不和を解決してエホバの恵みを得る”
という主題で考えてみましょう
“Settling Differences
Brings Jehovah’s Favor.”
それはマタイ 6章14節に
基づいています
It is based on Matthew 6:14.
Let’s read
this important verse together.
この重要な聖句を一緒に読みましょう
Right after teaching
his disciples how to pray,
弟子たちに祈りの仕方を教えたすぐ後
イエスは14節でこう述べました
Jesus says in verse 14:
“あなた方が人の罪過を許すなら—”
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
“あなた方の天の父もあなた方を
許してくださるのです”
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
To what extent do Jesus’ words
affect how Jehovah
この言葉はわたしたちの
日々の崇拝に対する—
views what we do each day
in our worship to him?
エホバの見方にどの程度影響しますか？
Consider this:
あなたは一日の終わりに
祈ろうとしています
You’re concluding
your day in prayer.
You pray for Jehovah’s name
to be sanctified.
エホバのお名前が
神聖なものとされるように
You pray
for his Kingdom to come.
王国が来ますように
You ask that he bless
the Governing Body
統治体や指導の任に当たっている
兄弟たちに祝福があるように
and the brothers taking the lead.
You share with him
a few matters
また個人的な心配事について祈ります
of personal concern.
And then you say: “Jehovah,
それからこう言います—
“エホバわたしは不完全で
たびたび罪を犯します”
“I know I am imperfect,
“and I sin against you often.
“Please forgive me
for my sins.
“どうぞ罪をお許しください”
“Let me stand before you
“どうぞみ前で清く是認された立場を
お与えください”
in a clean
and approved state.”
Now the question is,
さて問題は エホバはあなたの
心からの願いを聞かれるでしょうか？
Has Jehovah heard
your heartfelt request?
許してくださいますか？
Will he forgive you?
Well, what did Jesus say?
イエスは何と述べたでしょうか？
Look again at verse 14:
もう一度 14節を見てください
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
“あなた方が人の罪過を許すなら—”
“あなた方の天の父もあなた方を
許してくださるでしょう”
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
Did you notice
Jesus’ use of the word “if”?
イエスが条件を付けていることに
お気づきですか？
That tells us that forgiveness
is not automatic.
許しは自動的には与えられないのです
It comes with a condition, or price.
条件または代価が必要です
What price?
どんな代価ですか？
According to Jesus,
‘if we forgive others,’
イエスによればもしわたしたちが
“人の罪過を許すなら”—
the condition has been met;
条件は満たされ
代価は支払われたことになります
the price has been paid.
What will Jehovah do for us?
エホバはどうされますか？
Jesus said:
“[He] will also forgive you.”
“あなた方を許してくださる”
とイエスは述べました
Really, though,
is it fair or reasonable
“人を許した場合に限って あなた方を許そう”
とエホバがわたしたちに言われるのは—
for Jehovah to say to us,
‘Only if you forgive others,
公正で道理にかなったことでしょうか？
then I will also forgive you’?
Well, suppose you
get very sick and lose your job.
では重い病気になって
仕事を失ったと仮定してみてください
You’re unable
to pay rent for many months.
何か月も支払いができません
切迫した状況です
Your situation is desperate.
ほとんど打つ手がありません
You have very few,
if any, options.
妻や子供のことが心配です
You worry about your wife
and your children.
それで家主の所に行って—
Say you go to the owner
of the house and ask
回復するまで猶予を
与えてほしいと頼みます
if he would give you time
to get back on your feet.
Once you get better
and are able to work again,
良くなって働けるようになるなら—
負債を支払うために
何でも行なうつもりでいます
you will do everything
within your power
to pay him what you owe.
He tells you not to worry.
家主は大丈夫と言います
He understands your situation.
事情を理解し
負債をしばらく取り消してくれたので—
He will cancel your debt,
状況が良くなるまで
支払いする必要はなくなりました
and you do not have
to pay him any rent
until your situation improves.
In fact, he’ll cover
your monthly expenses
そして家族を世話できるようになるまで—
毎月の出費も賄ってくれることに
なったのです
until you are able
to care for your family.
How would you feel
about what he has done,
この人がしてくれたことをどう思いますか？
and would this affect
how you treat others?
それは他の人の扱い方に
どんな影響を及ぼしますか？
Well, because of our sinful nature,
罪深い傾向のゆえに—
わたしたちはエホバに負債を抱えており
死に値する者です
we are all in debt to Jehovah
—deserving of death.
We are unable
to cover our expenses.
自分では負債を支払えません
But when we go
to Jehovah in prayer
でも祈りでエホバに近づき
助けを求めるなら—
and beg for his help,
大きな憐れみと親切を示して
心配はいらないと言ってくださいます
in his great mercy and kindness,
he tells us not to worry.
He has given the life
of his Son to pay our debt.
わたしたちの負債のために
み子の命を与えてくださったのです
And on the basis of that sacrifice,
エホバはその犠牲に基づいて—
He is willing to cover our expenses
わたしたちが日々犯す罪に対する
支払いを喜んで行なってくださり—
—the sins we commit daily—
and to extend forgiveness
to us until we are able
新しい世でわたしたちが
完全になって回復を遂げるまで—
to get back on our feet,
許しを差し伸べてくださるのです
when we reach perfection
in the new world.
So think again about those
simple yet powerful words
マタイ 6章14節にある—
簡潔で力強いイエスの言葉を
もう一度考えてください
of Jesus at Matthew 6:14:
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
“あなた方が人の罪過を許すなら—”
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
“あなた方の天の父もあなた方を
許してくださるのです”
Is that fair?
それは公正で
道理にかなっていますか？
Is that reasonable?
Is it realistic?
実際的ですか？
Without a doubt!
その通りです！
In fact, settling differences,
実際 不和を解決し
惜しみなく許すことは—
or forgiving others freely,
is one of the best ways to imitate
エホバの同情心や憐れみ深い特質に
ならう最善の方法です
Jehovah’s compassionate
and merciful nature.
What can help us
to settle differences quickly?
不和を素早く解決する
助けがありますか？
The first thing
we should do is to try
最初にすべきことは 間違いを
愛で覆うようにすることです
and let love cover
over the wrong.
Can I just forgive and forget?
ただ許して忘れるのです
If we are able to do so,
そうできるなら—
それこそ会衆の平和と一致を保つ
素晴らしい方法となります
this is a beautiful way to maintain
the congregation’s peace and unity.
But if we’re struggling
to forget the wrong,
もしなかなか忘れることが
できないなら—
there are two scriptures
that are especially helpful
不和を解決する点で
特に助けとなる聖句が二つあります
in this matter
of settling differences.
They are Matthew 5:23, 24
それはマタイ 5章23, 24節と
マタイ 18章15-17節です
and Matthew 18:15-17.
Keep in mind that these texts
これらの聖句は同じ状況について
述べているのではありませんし—
are not referring
to the same scenarios,
全く同じように適用すべきものでもない
ことを思いに留めてください
nor are they to be applied
in the exact same way.
Matthew chapter 5
マタイ5章は適用範囲がより広く—
has a broader application
ほとんどの状況で平和を保つために
用いることができます
and can be used to bring peace
in most situations.
Matthew chapter 18
マタイ18章は適用範囲がより限定的で—
has a more limited application
and applies to specific situations
より深刻な性質の特定の状況に
当てはめるものです
that are more serious in nature.
Now let’s consider the first text,
では マタイ5章23, 24節を
考慮しましょう
Matthew 5:23, 24:
“それで供え物を祭壇に持って来て—”
“If, then,
you are bringing your gift to the altar
“兄弟が自分に対して
何か反感を抱いていることを—”
“and there you remember that
your brother has something against you,
“そこで思い出したならあなたの供え物を
そこ祭壇の前に残しておいて—”
“leave your gift there
in front of the altar, and go away.
”出かけて行きなさい”
“First make your peace
with your brother,
“まず自分の兄弟と和睦し—”
“それから戻って来たときに
あなたの供え物をささげなさい”
and then come back
and offer your gift.”
To truly capture
what these two brief verses mean
これらの節が今日のわたしたちに
どんな意味があるのかを理解するには—
for you and me today,
イエスの言葉が西暦１世紀の
ユダヤ人にとって—
we have to understand
what Jesus’ words meant
to his first-century Jewish listeners.
どんな意味があったのかを
理解しなければなりません
Picture the scene in your mind
as we transport ourselves
2千年前のエルサレムの都市に—
自分がいるところを
思い描いてみてください
into the city of Jerusalem
some 2,000 years ago.
It is during one
of the annual festivals.
毎年開かれる祭りの
一つに来ています
There are tens of thousands
of people in the city.
そには幾万もの人でごった返しています
You are there to make your sacrifice
—a beautiful lamb.
あなたは立派な子羊を
犠牲にしようとしています
The best one you have.
一番良いものです
It’s clean and unblemished.
きれいで傷がありません
You take the lamb
through a series of courts
あなたは子羊を携えて中庭を通り
祭司の中庭までやって来ます
all the way
to the Court of Priests.
It has taken you
most of the day to get there.
そこまで行くのにほぼ一日がかりです
Now you’re ready
to put your hands on that animal
やっと動物の上に手を置き罪の許しの
祈りをささげる準備ができましたが—
and offer a prayer for forgiveness,
and then you remember something.
そこであることを思い出します
What?
何でしょう?
Verse 23 reads:
23節をご覧ください
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
“兄弟が自分に対して
何か反感を抱いていることを—”
“and there you remember
that your brother
“そこで思い出したなら”……
has something against you,”
Now you think:
‘My brother
“兄弟は何か反感を抱いているに
違いない”とあなたは考えます
‘does have
something against me!
‘The last time I saw him,
“この前会った時 自分には
全くあいさつをしてくれなかった”
‘he greeted
everybody else but me.
‘He was upset.
But what is it?
“怒っていたけど
何があったんだろう？”
‘I don’t remember
doing anything.
“全く身に覚えはないけれど—”
‘He is so sensitive!
“敏感すぎるんだよ！”
“いつも何か 気にいらない
ことがあるみたいだ”
He’s always upset
with something.’
Did Jesus
have all of that in mind
イエスはそういうことを念頭に置いて
23節を語られたのでしょうか？
when he said
what he did in verse 23?
No!
いいえ
He did not go into detail
イエスはその“何か”がどういう事か
詳細を述べられませんでした
about what
that “something” might be.
He doesn’t say
who is right or wrong.
どちらが正しいかも述べていません
He doesn’t make a comment
その人が繊細で いつも怒りっぽく—
about whether
someone is too sensitive,
納得せず 人とうまくやっていけない人だ
ということについて何も述べていません
always getting upset,
never satisfied,
difficult to get along with.
Why not?
なぜですか?
Because the reason
behind the “something”
それは何が原因だったかということは
重要ではないからです
is not the important thing.
What is the important thing?
重要なのは何ですか？
That the peace
has been disturbed.
平和が損なわれていることです！
There is a difference
that needs to be settled.
解決すべき不和がそこにあったのです
The lack of peace
between brothers
兄弟間の平和の欠如は
エホバとの関係に影響します
could affect their relationship
with Jehovah.
That is important!
エホバとの関係こそ重要です！
So what should be done?
では何をすべきですか？
We see the answer in verse 24:
24節に答えがあります
“Leave your gift there
“あなたの供え物をそこ
祭壇の前に残しておいて—”
“in front of the altar,
and go away.
“出かけてゆきなさい”
“まず自分の兄弟と和睦し—”
“First make your peace
with your brother,
“それから戻って来たときに
あなたの供え物をささげなさい”
and then come back
and offer your gift.”
That animal sacrifice
is important too.
その動物の犠牲も重要です
それは間違いありません
There’s no doubt about that.
It represents worship to Jehovah
それはエホバへの崇拝を表わしており—
—like going to the meetings,
in the field service,
集会の出席や野外奉仕
また家族の崇拝などが含まれます
sharing in family worship.
But according to Jesus,
しかしイエスによれば
もっと重要なものは何ですか？
what is more important?
It is settling the difference
それは不和を解決すること
まず兄弟たちとの平和を作ることです
—making peace
with our brother first.
Then we will be
in an acceptable position
そうするならエホバの崇拝の供え物を—
ささげるのにふさわしい
立場に立てるのです
to offer our gift
of worship to Jehovah.
Yes, settling differences
will bring Jehovah’s favor.
不和を解決することは
エホバの恵みをもたらします
But when can we apply
the principle of Matthew 5?
でも マタイ5章の原則を
いつ適用できますか？
Whenever there is
a difference to be settled.
解決すべき不和があるならいつでもです
Perhaps our brother
misunderstood what we said or did.
自分の言動が誤解されるかもしれません
Or maybe he didn’t misunderstand
誤解ではなく 兄弟が傷つくような—
—maybe we did give him
a valid reason to be hurt.
明確な理由をこちらが
作ったのかもしれません
Regardless, we notice
いずれにしても兄弟が
傷ついたことに気付きます
that he has something against us.
In that case, we make peace.
その場合 平和な関係を作ります
We can also use
the principles of this text
また自分が傷つけられたり
兄弟に対して反感を抱いている場合も—
when we are hurt
or have something
この聖句の原則を適用します
against our brother.
We can take the initiative ourselves
率先して行動し 誤解を解き
不和を解決し—
to settle misunderstandings,
to resolve differences,
兄弟たちとの平和を作ることができます
and to make peace
with our brother.
この場合も エホバはそうした精神を
祝福されます
Again, Jehovah blesses
such a spirit.
Now, open your Bible
to Matthew chapter 18.
では次に マタイ18章を
開いてみましょう
We mentioned earlier that it has
初めに述べたようにこの聖句の適用は
さらに限定的なものです
a more limited application.
How so?
どのようにですか?
15節をご覧ください
Notice verse 15:
“さらにもしあなたの兄弟が罪を犯したなら—”
“Moreover,
if your brother commits a sin,
“行ってただあなたと彼との間で
その過ちを明らかにしなさい”
“go and reveal his fault
between you and him alone.
“彼があなたの述べることを聴くなら
あなたは自分の兄弟を得たのです”
If he listens to you,
you have gained your brother.”
Here Jesus says,
“if your brother commits a sin.”
ここでイエスは “あなたの兄弟が
罪を犯したなら”と言いました
That is much different
than just having
それは “何か反感を”いだくこととは
大きな違いです
“something against [us].”
We are talking about a situation
that is much more serious.
これはもっと重大な状況について
述べているのです
What situation?
どんな状況ですか？
The revised
Organized to Do Jehovah’s Will book,
改訂版の「エホバのご意志を行なう」
の136, 7ページによると—
page 136, explains
それは“借りたお金を返さない場合や
詐欺を働いた場合など金銭や財産の—”
that it “involves financial
or property matters,
“such as failing to repay a loan
“関係した問題であると思われます”
“or committing fraud.
“Or the offense
might be slander,
“その過ちには中傷が含まれるかもしれません”
which seriously affects
someone’s reputation.”
“人の評判をひどく傷つけたような場合です”
とあります
Of course,
they are sins that could be resolved
もちろん関係者同士で解決できる罪も
ありますが もし解決できなければ—
between the individuals concerned
but are also serious enough
to merit expulsion
from the congregation if not settled.
会衆から追放されるほど
由々しい罪もあります
Before we start applying
Matthew 18:15,
マタイ 18章15節を適用する前に—
we should first consider
whether it is really necessary
その段階を本当にとる必要があるか
どうかをまず考慮すべきです
to pursue the matter.
Could we simply
forgive the individual
その人がしたことや
経済的に被った損失で—
for what was done
or even take the loss
その人をただ許すことは
できないでしょうか?
if it were a financial matter?
That is a personal decision.
それは個人が決めることです
If we decide to pursue the matter,
物事を進めるのであれば
どのようにしますか？
what do we do?
Jesus helps us in verse 15,
when he says
イエスは15節で ただ二人の間で
過ちを明らかにしなさいと述べています
that we reveal his fault
between the two of us alone.
We do not discuss
the matter with others,
だれかとその件を話し合って—
自分の味方につけよう
としてはなりません
attempting to get them
to side with us.
We do not go
straight to the elders
直接 長老の所に行って二人の問題を
解決してもらおうとしてはなりません
and try to get them
to solve the problem for us.
No, we try to resolve
the matter between us.
そうではなく二人で解決すべきなのです
And since our goal
is to settle the difference,
目標は不和を解決して
エホバとの関係を保ち—
maintain our relationship
with Jehovah,
兄弟も同様にするよう
助けることですから—
and help our brother do the same,
we make repeated efforts
to speak with him
初めの努力が成功しなくても
繰り返し話し合う努力を払います
when our initial efforts
are unsuccessful.
Keep in mind
that Jesus did not say:
イエスは “誤りを明らかにするために
一度だけ行きなさい”とは言われませんでした
“Go only once
and reveal his fault.”
When applying this first step,
make it clear
この最初の段階を進めるとき—
その動機が“兄弟を得る”ため
であることを忘れないでください
that your motive
is to ‘gain your brother.’
Also, it would be helpful
to clearly state
また 自分はマタイ 18章15節でイエスが述べた—
that you are applying
the first step in settling differences
最初の段階を適用しようとしていることを
はっきりと述べることは助けになるでしょう
as outlined by Jesus
at Matthew 18:15.
Of course,
this would be stated in a kindly,
もちろん親切に 脅すような仕方ではなく
この問題を解決することが—
nonthreatening manner
but still in a way
to show the seriousness
重大な事であることを示すような
仕方で伝えます
of getting the matter settled.
What if the first step
兄弟を得る最初の段階が
うまく行かなかったならどうしますか？
in gaining your brother
is unsuccessful?
Notice verse 16 explains step 2:
16節の第2段階に注目してください
“But if he does not listen,
“しかし もし彼が聴かないなら—”
“take along with you
one or two more,
“あなたと一緒にあと一人か二人を
連れて行きなさい”
“so that on the testimony
of two or three witnesses
“一切のことが二人または三人の証人の
口によって確証されるためです”
every matter
may be established.”
Yes, we talk with him
in the company of one or two more.
そうです 一人か二人を伴って
話すのです
Would that be our best friends?
あなたの親友を連れて行くのですか？
No.
いいえ
目的は “兄弟を得る”ことです
The whole purpose
is to ‘gain our brother.’
Teaming up with two
of our best friends
二人の友人とチームになるなら
兄弟を孤立させてしまいます
could alienate our brother.
Instead, it makes sense
代わりに他の円熟した
クリスチャンを伴うなら受け入れやすいでしょう
that we would choose
other mature Christians.
How would mature Christians
be helpful?
彼らはどのように
助けになるでしょうか？
Well, are we
misunderstanding things?
物事を誤解しているでしょうか？
Could they help him
to reason about the matter?
正しく推論するよう
助けになれますか？
Could a solution be found?
解決策を見出せますか?
Having spiritually
mature witnesses there
霊的に円熟した証人がそこにいれば
問題を解決する助けになるでしょう
may help to resolve the matter.
Generally, applying steps 1
大抵は 第一か第二の段階で
兄弟を得て—
and 2 will result
in gaining your brother
会衆の平和が保たれる
結果となることでしょう
and preserving the peace
of the congregation.
If he does not respond
to these repeated efforts
助けようとする繰り返しの努力に
答え応じない場合はどうなりますか？
to help him, then what?
You have a decision to make.
あなたが決定します
Are you willing
to forgive your brother,
経済的な損失が生じてもそれを受け入れ
あなたの兄弟を進んで許しますか？
even take a loss
if a financial matter is involved?
If you choose
to pursue the matter further,
もしさらに事を進めるのであれば—
17節のイエスの言葉に
耳を傾けてください
listen to Jesus’ words recorded
at verse 17:
“If he does not listen to them,
“もし彼がそれらの人たちの述べることを
聴かないなら会衆に話しなさい”
“speak to the congregation.
“If he does not listen
even to the congregation,
“もし会衆の告げることにさえ
聴かないならその人を—”
“let him be to you
just as a man of the nations
“あなたにとって諸国民の者
また収税人のような者としなさい”
and as a tax collector.”
At this point,
the body of elders
この段階で会衆を代表している
長老たちがかかわってきます
representing the congregation
will get involved.
They will review
the facts of the case and determine
長老たちは問題の事実を見直し
審理委員会を設ける必要があるかを決定します
if a judicial committee
should be appointed.
Happily, though,
these situations are rare,
幸いにもこうした状況はまれで—
問題は重大な段階に行く前に平和裏に
解決されることが少なくありません
and matters
are often resolved peacefully
before reaching
such a serious point.
あの心からのエホバへの祈りに
もう一度戻ってみましょう
Think back again
to that heartfelt prayer to Jehovah.
Has Jehovah heard
our sincere requests?
エホバは心からの願いを
聞いてくださるでしょうか？
Will he forgive?
許してくださいますか？
Well, at this moment,
ところで今 解決しなければならない
兄弟との不和があることに気付いているなら—
if you realize there is a difference
with your brother
that needs to be settled,
その点についてエホバに祈ってください
pray to Jehovah about the matter.
Ask him to help you see
感情を克服して 平和を作れるよう
エホバの助けを求めてください
beyond the emotion
and make peace.
Do not let any more time go by!
決して後回しにしないでください！
Once we have followed
the simple steps outlined by Jesus
イエスが述べた簡潔な方法に従って
他の人を許すなら—
and have forgiven others,
条件は整っていることになります
the condition has been met;
the price has been paid.
あなたは犠牲を払ったのです
Then what will Jehovah
do for us?
ではエホバは何をなさいますか？
Jesus said:
イエスは”父も許してくださる”
と述べました
‘He will also forgive us.’
As a result,
we will gain the peace of mind
その結果 エホバの恵みと
祝福を得ることから来る—
that comes with a clean conscience,
清い良心を伴う思いの平安を
得ることができます
knowing that we have
Jehovah’s favor and blessing.
そのようにして
わたしたちがその一部となっている—
We can then
make a valuable contribution
美しい一致した兄弟関係に
大いに貢献することができるのです
to the beautiful,
united brotherhood
that we are privileged
to be a part of.
There are more lessons
in Matthew chapter 18
マタイ18章には—
兄弟たちと平和や一致を保つ方法
に関する教訓がほかにもあります
that teach us how to maintain peace
and unity with our brothers.
Just as important
as settling differences,
不和を解決するのが
重要であるのと同様—
イエスは人をつまずかせないように
注意しなさいと言われました
Jesus cautioned against becoming
a cause for stumbling.
ベテルの朝の崇拝で
スティーブン・レット兄弟は—
At a Bethel morning worship,
Brother Stephen Lett described
人をつまずかせないための
3つの方法を説明しました
three ways
we can avoid stumbling others.
Now, this word picture
“つまずく”というこの絵画的表現は
思いに鮮明に描くことができます
of someone being stumbled
is quite vivid, isn’t it?
We’ve all seen someone stumbled.
皆 だれかがつまずくのを
見たことがあり—
In fact, we’ve all stumbled
ourselves at times,
自分自身つまずくこともあります
and there are varying degrees
of consequences.
その結果の程度は様々です
For example,
a person can stumble,
たとえば つまずいても
すぐにバランスを取り戻し—
quickly recover,
and continue
almost uneventfully down the path.
何事もなく歩き続けることがあります
Or a person can stumble,
また つまずいて倒れ 骨を折り—
fall, break a bone,
大掛かりな治療をして
ようやく回復する場合もあります
eventually they recover
—but only after extensive therapy.
Then again, a person can stumble,
あるいは つまずいて
倒れ 頭を打ち—
fall, hit his head,
never recover
二度と回復せずに
犠牲者となるかもしれません
—becoming a casualty.
Well, the situation is similar
霊的につまずく場合も同様です
when one is stumbled spiritually.
すぐに回復する場合もあれば—
He can recover quickly,
回復まで時間がかかる場合—
maybe recover over time,
あるいは二度と回復せずに
霊的な犠牲者となる場合もあります
or he may never recover
—becoming a spiritual casualty.
だれかがつまずくと最終的に
どんな結果になるかは分かりません
So we cannot know
the ultimate outcome
for someone who is stumbled.
それで 注意深くあって—
So no wonder we’re cautioned
to be very careful
決してつまずきの原因とならないように
との警告が与えられているのです
to never be any cause
for stumbling.
Open up
to Matthew chapter 18,
マタイ 18章を開きましょう
and here’s
an especially powerful scripture
この点で特に力強い聖句があります
in this regard.
マタイ 18章6節でイエスは
こう述べておられます
Matthew 18:6, Jesus says:
“But whoever stumbles
one of these little ones
“しかし わたしに信仰を置く—”
“これら小さな者の一人を
つまずかせるのがだれであっても—”
“who have faith in me,
“it would be better for him
to have hung around his neck
“その者にとっては ろばの回す
ような臼石を首にかけられて—”
“a millstone
that is turned by a donkey
and to be sunk in the open sea.”
“広い大海に沈められるほうが
益になります”
Well, with graphic language,
イエスは写実的な言葉を使い
だれかを霊的な犠牲者にするなら—
Jesus describes
how that if we cause someone
to become a spiritual casualty,
永遠の滅びを自分自身にもたらす
と述べておられるのです
we could actually bring
eternal doom
upon ourselves.
でもここで質問が生じます
But now, here’s a question,
What could we do
to cause someone to stumble?
どのようにつまずかせて
しまうのでしょうか？
Well, interestingly,
there are several similarities
興味深いことに—
だれかを物理的に
つまずかせることと—
between causing someone
to stumble physically
霊的につまずかせることには
共通点があります
and causing someone
to stumble spiritually.
Let us discuss three.
3つの点を考えましょう
Now one, pushing someone
一つ目に だれかを押すことは
つまずきの原因となります
could cause them to stumble,
especially if they’re on uneven terrain,
if you think about it.
特にでこぼこ道ではそう言えます
And this is true
physically and spiritually.
これは物理的にも霊的にも真実です
But think about Jehovah
for a moment.
エホバについて考えてみてください
He could push any of us,
couldn’t he?
だれかを押して ご自身に仕えるよう
強制することもおできになりますが—
He could force us to serve him.
He certainly has the power,
but he never uses it that way.
決して力をそのように
お用いになりません
Instead, he invites, he encourages;
代わりに 招待し 励まし
決定の結果の祝福や呪いを説明されます
and he explains the blessings,
the curses,
depending upon how we decide.
But it’s up to us, isn’t it?
それでも 決定は
各自にかかっています
For example, at Isaiah 48:18,
たとえば イザヤ 48章18節で
こう述べておられます
Jehovah says: ‘If only
‘you would pay attention
to my commandments!
“ああ あなたがわたしのおきてに
実際に注意を払いさえすれば！”
‘Then your peace
would become like a river
“そうすれば あなたの平安は
川のように—”
and your righteousness
like the waves of the sea.’
“あなたの義は
海の波のようになるであろうに”
Beseeching, but not forcing.
強制せずに 訴えておられます
Now think about it,
if Jehovah doesn’t force,
そうであれば—
わたしたちが強制することも
望まれないのではないでしょうか？
he doesn’t want us
to force either, does he?
For example, parents
たとえば 親は子どもを押して—
need to be very careful
they don’t just simply push
エホバに仕えさせることが
ないよう注意すべきです
their children to serve Jehovah.
But rather, lovingly,
かえって エホバのように
愛情深く心に訴え—
beseechingly like Jehovah,
try to reach the heart,
and of course,
どんな祝福があるかを
はっきり示しましょう
clearly show them the blessings
that will come their way
if they do.
Another example,
別の例として 長老はエホバの羊を
決して押してはなりません
elders should never try
to push Jehovah’s sheep.
I heard an experience
about an elder, during his part,
ある長老は自分の割り当ての中で—
asked the brothers
for a show of hands
翌朝奉仕に出る人に
手を挙げてもらいました
how many were going out in service
the next morning.
Well, only a few raised their hand.
少ししか手が挙がらないのを見ると—
He proceeded
to scold the congregation
もっと出るべきだと会衆を叱りつけ
浅はかにも再び挙手を求めました
that more should be going out.
Well, he then unwisely asked
for another show of hands.
You guessed it
—fewer raised their hand
お察しのとおり 二回目は
さらに減りました
the second time.
Take another example,
ほかの例として
聖書研究の司会者は—
those who conduct Bible studies
should not just try to push
their students to do the right thing.
正しいことを行なうよう
研究生を押すべきではありません
“You’ve got to quit smoking!
You’ve got to get rid of those idols!”
“たばこをやめなさい！
偶像を処分しなさい！”
No, not with external pressure,
そのような圧力ではなく—
but by motivating their hearts,
心に動機づけを与えれば
研究生は行動します
you motivate your students.
Or take another example,
none of us
さらに別の例として
学校の友達 同僚 親族を押して—
should try to push schoolmates,
workmates, or relatives
to accept the truth.
真理を受け入れさせようと
すべきではありません
A pushing approach,
shoving approach
—even though motivated with sincerity—
押して圧力をかける方法は
たとえ誠実さゆえであっても—
has actually resulted
in people being stumbled
人々をつまずかせ
何年もの間真理から遠ざけてしまいます
away from the truth
for many years.
It makes me think of the story,
or the saying,
このことは ある人が
真理を学び始めたら—
that when a person
first learns the truth,
問題を起こさないよう
6か月間閉じ込めておくべき—
you should lock them up
for about six months
to contain, or minimize,
the damage they do.
という言葉を思い起こさせます
しかし それはまったくの誤りです
Well, that saying is totally erroneous.
You shouldn’t lock that brother up;
you should follow that brother.
その熱意ある兄弟を
閉じ込めるのではなく—
むしろ 見倣うべきです
See, that brother has zeal,
doesn’t he?
その兄弟が興奮のあまり
親族や他の人に真理を強制しないよう—
But it’s true,
we probably do need to help him
to properly channel that zeal,
so that he doesn’t try
to force his relatives
熱意を正しい方向に向ける
助けがおそらく必要でしょう
or others to accept the truth
that he is so excited about.
But now, what is the second thing
では 二番目のつまずきの
原因は何でしょうか？
we can do to cause someone
to stumble?
Placing an obstacle in their path.
道に障害物を置くことです
Now again, this is true
physically or spiritually.
物理的にも霊的にもそう言えます
And if you think about it,
意図的であろうと
無意識であろうと—
whether we put
that stumbling block there intentionally
つまずきのもとを置くなら
結果は同じです
or unintentionally,
the result is the same, isn’t it?
今日の「ものみの塔」誌の
注解に述べられているように—
As mentioned
in today’s Watchtower comments,
健全な話し方をし
廉直に行動するなら—
wholesome speech and upright conduct
can help us to avoid
決してつまずきのもとを
置かないよう守られます
ever being a cause for stumbling.
In contrast, unwholesome speech,
対照的に 不健全な話し方や
汚れた行ないは—
unclean conduct,
can easily stumble ones inside
会衆内外の人をつまずかせます
or outside the congregation.
But now, what about in an area
では あることを行なう聖書的な
権利がある場合はどうでしょうか？
where we have a Scriptural right
to do something?
Now, surely exercising that right,
その権利を行使して
だれかがつまずいても—
if it stumbles someone,
言い開きを求められるはずはない
と言えるでしょうか？
we can’t be held accountable
for that, can we?
Well, open up
to 1 Corinthians chapter 8,
コリント第一 8章を開きましょう
and here
—very interestingly—
ここにとても興味深い答えがあります
this scripture
answers that question.
1 Corinthians 8:9,
コリント第一 8章9節
it says:
“But keep watching
“しかし あなた方のこの権限が
弱い人たちを何かのことで—”
“that your right to choose
“つまずかせるものとならないよう
いつも見守っていなさい”
“does not somehow
become a stumbling block
to those who are weak.”
興味深いと思いませんか？
Isn’t that interesting?
この聖句によれば
選ぶ権利があっても—
Even our right to choose,
だれかをつまずかせる可能性があるなら
その権利を行使しないのです
if it would stumble someone,
we wouldn’t exercise that right
according to this scripture.
The apostle Paul,
in verse 13 of that same chapter,
使徒パウロは同じ章の13節で
兄弟をつまずかせるなら—
he said he
wouldn’t even eat meat ever again
もはや二度と肉を食べない
と述べています
if it stumbled his brother.
Well, like Paul,
are we willing
わたしたちは ひげを生やすこと—
to forgo our rights regarding,
厚化粧をすること
アルコールを用いることなど—
for example,
wearing a beard,
wearing heavy makeup,
using alcohol
—as just a few examples—
もしだれかをつまずかせかねないなら—
if exercising that right
パウロと同じように喜んで
その権利を放棄するでしょうか？
might even possibly stumble someone?
But now,
what’s the third way
次に つまずかせる三番目の
原因は何でしょうか？
we could cause someone to stumble?
Failing to warn him
危険について警告しないことです
about a potential trip hazard.
これは手落ちの罪と言えます
We could call this
the sin of omission.
これも 物理的 霊的に当てはまります
And again,
it applies physically and spiritually.
物理的な例として 床にモップが
かけられたのを見たとしましょう
As a physical example,
let’s say we see the floor
has just been mopped,
ある人が知らずに濡れた部分に
近づいてきます
and an unsuspecting person
is approaching that wet area.
警告するでしょうか？
Now will we warn them?
もし警告せずに その人が
倒れて怪我をすれば—
If we don’t warn them
—they fall, hurt themselves—
わたしたちも幾らか責任を
負うのではないでしょうか？
would we not share
some responsibility?
Well, similarly,
同様に 霊的にだれかがそれと知らずに
“誤った歩み”をするとき—
with spiritual application,
Galatians 6:1 tells us
ガラテア 6章1節は何をするようにと
述べているでしょうか？
that if someone “takes a false step”
before he’s aware of it,
what are we supposed
to try to do?
そのような人に“再調整を
施すことに努め”—
“Try to readjust” such a person,
but then it adds:
“In a spirit of mildness.”
しかも“温和な霊をもって”
そうします
Don’t push him!
押すのではなく
優しく 愛情深く警告し—
But try to gently, lovingly warn
再調整を施すことに努めるのです
and readjust that person.
So there we have three areas
決してつまずきの原因とならないよう—
in which we must be careful
we never contribute
注意深くあるべき
三つの分野を考慮しました
toward someone being stumbled.
We don’t push others
to serve Jehovah.
エホバに仕えるよう
他の人を押さないこと
We strive to never,
たとえ無意識であったとしても
個人の権利を主張するなどして—
even unintentionally,
put a stumbling block in their path
—for example—
つまずきのもとを置くことが
決してないようにすること
by insisting on exercising
our personal rights.
And number three,
we never fail to lovingly warn
三つ目に 危険に近づく人がいるなら
愛情深く警告することです
one whom we see approaching
a potential trip hazard.
わたしたちは
つまずきの原因ではなく—
Rather than being
any cause for stumbling,
良いことを行なう力になりたいと
思うのではないでしょうか？
we want to be
a force for good, don’t we?
堅く立つよう助け—
Helping others to stand firm
倒れた人が起き上がるよう
助けるのです
and even helping ones get up
if they have fallen.
None of us want to cause
our brother to stumble,
だれも兄弟たちを
つまずかせたくありませんが—
but it can happen
if we’re not careful.
注意しないとそうなり得ます
Why not recall the three ways
人をつまずかせないための
3つの方法を思い起こしましょう
Brother Lett listed
to avoid stumbling others?
そして親 長老 聖書の教え手
また会衆の仲間の崇拝者として—
You can then examine
how you’re doing as a parent,
an elder, a Bible teacher,
or as a fellow worshipper
in the congregation.
自分はどう行動しているかを
吟味することができます
The effort we make toward unity
is always worthwhile.
一致のために払う努力は
いつでも価値があります
We want only joyful memories
兄弟姉妹たちと一緒に働いた年月の
喜ばしい思い出だけを残したいものです
of the years spent
working side by side
with our brothers and sisters.
73年間の特別全時間
奉仕を振り返って—
That’s the way
Sister Esther Lozano looks back
エスター・ロサーノ姉妹は
同様に感じています
on 73 years
of special full-time service.
Well, everybody here
calls me Honey, but my name
みんな “ハニー”って呼ぶけれど
名前はエスター・ロサーノです
is Esther Lozano.
And I was born in Fresno, California,
1919年に カリフォルニアの
フレズノで生まれました
in 1919.
I was baptized in 1935,
1935年にバプテスマを受けてから—
エホバへの奉仕を
本当に楽しんできました
and I’ve thoroughly enjoyed
my service to Jehovah.
I became a special pioneer,
その後 特別開拓者になり
それからギレアデに招待されました
and then they called me to Gilead.
I was in the fourth class of Gilead.
ギレアデの第4期です
1944年のことでした
That was in 1944.
特別開拓奉仕を離れるときには—
When I left my assignment as a special,
どんな勉強をするのかさえ
見当もつきませんでしたが—
I didn’t even know how it was to study,
but this was beautiful
ギレアデで受ける教育を
楽しみにしていました
how Gilead prepared us
for what was in the future.
Right after Gilead,
卒業するとすぐ—
エスター・ロペス姉妹と共に
2年間 ブルックリンベテルで働き—
we went to Brooklyn Bethel for two years
—Esther Lopez and I—
その後 わたしは
メキシコに遣わされました
then I was sent to Mexico.
I came in 1947,
and I’m still here.
1947年にメキシコに来てから
ずっとここにいます
So that makes more than 68 years
I’ve been in Mexico.
もう68年以上になります
When I arrived,
there were 7 Bethelites,
来た当時 ベテル奉仕者は7人
宣教者が22人でした
and there were 22 missionaries.
We all lived right at the branch;
宣教者も支部で一緒に暮らしました
it was a branch-missionary home.
The progress in Mexico
メキシコでの業の進展は
家族の一致と関係しています
really is because of the families
being united.
And when you get
the husband and wife together,
夫と妻が真理を学べば
家族みんなも学びます
then the whole family
comes in the truth.
1961年に—
In 1961, Sister Esther Lozano
preached to our grandparents.
エスター・ロサーノ姉妹が
祖父母に証言してくれました
祖父は ”失楽園から復楽園まで”の
本を通して関心を持ちました
My grandfather first got interested
through the book
From Paradise Lost to Paradise Regained.
奥さんは 本を受け取ると
ご主人に渡しました
When I placed the book
with his wife
and she gave it to him,
he decided that that’s what
he was looking for.
これこそ自分が探していたものだ
と確信した彼は—
He said,
“Well, when can I be baptized?”
“いつバプテスマを受けられますか？”
って言ったんです
Three visits later,
3回の訪問の後
家族全員が研究に加わりました
a study was started
with the entire family.
And the oldest son was only 13.
一番上の息子さんは
まだ13歳でしたが—
“僕もバプテスマを受ける！”
と言いました
He said,
“I’m getting baptized too!”
About a year ago, he came
1年ほど前に
彼が手紙を持って来てくれました
and brought me a letter
and told me how happy he was
そして 自分の家に証言に来てくれて
本当に嬉しかったと言ってくれたんです
that I had gone to their home
and preached to them.
わたしの人生における
幸福な経験です
And that was
a happy experience of my life.
今では 家族の23人が 四世代に
わたってエホバの証人です
Today, in our family,
we are 23 Witnesses
spread over four generations,
わたしは兄と一緒に
中央アメリカ支部で奉仕しています
and now my brother
and I are serving here
at the Central America branch.
Oh, I forgot to talk about my husband.
主人のことを忘れていました
He was the branch overseer at that time.
彼は 支部の監督でした
We were there
in the same branch for five years.
同じ支部で5年ほど働いていたので—
お互いのことをよく知っていましたが—
We got to know each other,
but I didn’t pay attention to him
奉仕が忙しくて
あまり気にしていませんでした
because I was always in the service.
And so,
I don’t know when he decided
結婚が 彼の人生の目標でない
ことは知っていたので—
he wanted to get married
because I know
結婚しようと決意したなんて
気づきませんでした
that wasn’t his goal in life.
And so I wrote Brother Knorr
ノア兄弟に手紙を書いて—
and asked him if he was surprised
“わたしたちが結婚すると聞いたら
驚きますか”と尋ねました
to hear that we
were going to be married.
Then he did write me back
そうしたら 兄弟は返事をくれました
and also said,
well this is what he said in the letter:
手紙の中でノア兄弟は—
‘You’re always jolly
and talkative when I’m around.
“陽気で話し好きな あなたと—”
“とても物静かな ロサーノ兄弟“
‘On the other hand,
‘Brother Lozano is so quiet.
“非常に興味深い
組み合わせですね”
‘I must say,
it is an interesting combination.
“お二人が一緒なら—
‘Both of you together
can serve him and aid
真の崇拝において互いに
助け合っていけるでしょう”—
one another in your true worship.’
と言ってくださいました
This is one of my greatest treasures,
兄弟からの手紙は
一番大切な宝物の一つです
having that letter from Brother Knorr.
Then when Rudy died,
ルディーが亡くなったとき
そのことで くよくよしませんでした
I didn’t dwell on that.
I remembered
I made my dedication to Jehovah,
自分はエホバに献身していること
そして それを第一にするよう—
and I know that he would want me
to put that first in my life.
神が望んでおられることを
思い起こしました
So I did not really suffer
神権的な活動に
一層打ち込むようにしたので—
that much about his death
because I became even more involved
主人の死を過度に
悲しむことはありませんでした
in theocratic activities.
I’m in the Correspondence.
今は 通信部門にいます
But I’m at work
about an hour and a half in the morning
でも 働くのは
午前と午後の1時間半ずつで—
and an hour and a half
in the afternoon
and the rest of the time
それ以外の時間は部屋で研究しています
I’m studying here in the room.
I’m so pleased that I’m still able
まだ 朝の崇拝に出席し—
to go to the morning text,
奉仕にも参加できることを
嬉しく思っています
and I have a part in the service.
I have two studies
that I conduct every week.
毎週 二件の研究を司会しています
エホバに自分の命を捧げた人たちと
共にいられるのは喜びです
It’s such a pleasure
to be with people
that have dedicated
their lives to Jehovah.
エホバが 彼らを—
And that’s what makes me happy
because I know
ご自分の大切な息子や娘たち
とみなしておられるので—
Jehovah counts them
as his precious sons and daughters.
わたしも幸せです
I don’t know why,
どういう訳か
宣教者の多くが訪ねてきてくれて—
but many of the missionaries
have come up to me and told me
わたしが励みになってきたと
言ってくれます
that I’ve been
an encouragement to them,
and really,
they are the ones that encourage me.
でも彼らこそ
わたしの励みです
It’s because I had
such beautiful examples
長年にわたり 見倣うべき
素晴らしい手本に囲まれてきました
to follow in all these years.
神にお仕えできる
素晴らしい特権について—
And all I can say
is thanks to Jehovah
わたしはただ—
for this great privilege
of serving him.
エホバに感謝しています
ロサーノ姉妹は
割り当てに留まり—
Sister Lozano is a beautiful example
人々と親しい友情の絆を結ぶ点で
素晴らしい模範です
of sticking to your assignment
and building
close bonds of friendship.
Did you notice
another blessing she enjoyed?
姉妹が得たほかの祝福にも
気付かれましたか？
It was finding a marriage mate
それは全時間奉仕の目標を共にした
配偶者を見いだしたことです
who shared her goals
for full-time service.
Of course,
not every courtship leads to marriage.
すべての交際が結婚に
至るわけではありません
If you’re dating,
can you look past your emotions
交際中でお互いに
気持ちがあるとしても—
あなたは配偶者となる人との
違いや欠点を—
to honestly see the differences
正直に見ることができますか？
and flaws
in your potential mate?
Can you accept these?
それを受け入れますか？
それとも関係を終わらせるほど
重大な問題でしょうか？
Or are they serious enough
for you to end your courtship?
That’s the situation
depicted in the third
“結婚に備える”シリーズの3番目の
最後のビデオではこの状況が描かれます
and final part of the series
Preparing for Marriage.
Well, the big day finally arrived.
ついに大切な日が来ました
After all those months of preparation,
数か月準備し 想像した通りです
it was just as I imagined.
Oh wait!
あっ 待って!—
That’s not me.
彼女じゃなくて...
That’s me.
こっちがわたしです
As I watched my sister
get married that day,
その日 妹が結婚するのを見て—
I couldn’t help
but think about my own future.
自分の将来を考えさせられました
When I began dating Shane,
シェーンと付き合い始めた時—
everything was perfect.
すべてがうまくいっていました
We spent a lot of time
talking on the phone.
何時間も電話で話しました
Everything just naturally
seemed to click.
お互いにひかれ合っていたんです
I was convinced he was the one.
彼だと確信していました
But over time,
I started to notice some things.
でも 徐々に気になることが
出てきました
I was starting to see patterns.
彼の傾向が見え始めたんです
And they didn’t seem
to be getting better.
改善していくとも思えませんでした
I wasn’t even sure
our goals were the same anymore.
目標が同じかどうかも
分からなくなりました
I felt alone.
独りぼっちみたい...
But thankfully, I wasn’t.
でも そうではなかったんです
My mom kindly asked
how things were going,
母は優しく様子を聞いてくれたので—
so I told her.
気持ちを話せました
“Maybe he’s not the one,”
I told her.
“多分 彼ではないと思う...”
I thought she was going to tell me
どうすべきか言われる
と思っていたけれど—
which way I should go,
but she didn’t.
違いました
Instead, she reassured me
“彼でなくてもあなたは大丈夫よ”
と言って安心させてくれました
that if he wasn’t the one,
I was going to be OK.
They reminded me about what Jesus said
when building a tower.
塔を建てる際にイエスが言われたことを
思い起こさせてくれました
“たとえば あなた方のうちのだれが
塔を建てようと思う場合—”
“For example, who of you
wanting to build a tower
“does not first sit down
and calculate the expense
“まず座って費用を計算し—”
“自分がそれを完成するだけのものを
持っているかどうかを—”
to see if he has enough
to complete it?”
“調べないでしょうか？”
I realized that I was about to enter
into a building project of my own
わたしは “シェーンとの関係”という—
建設プロジェクトを
始めようとしていたんです
—my relationship with Shane—
and I too needed
to “calculate the expense”
だからそれにとりかかる前に
“費用を計算する”必要もあるんです
before I commit to it.
They encouraged me
to talk to Shane
両親は 心配していることを—
and tell him about the things
that were concerning me.
シェーンと話し合うよう
励ましてくれました
So I did.
そうしました
And my mom was right.
母の言ったとおり—
わたしは大丈夫でした
I was OK, more than OK, really.
本当に大丈夫だったんです
Shane and I decided it was best
to break off the relationship.
わたしはシェーンと
別れることにしました
数年後—
And some years later,
自分と同じようにエホバを
愛している兄弟に出会いました
I found someone
that loves Jehovah as much as I do,
and I love him with my whole heart.
心から彼を愛しています
姉妹は賢明にも自分のことを
建設プロジェクトと比較しました
Our sister wisely compared
her relationship
to a building project.
She “calculated the expense”
交際期間中に見たすべての特質の
“費用を計算”しました
of any traits she saw
during their courtship
—well before they
could become problems in a marriage.
結婚で問題を抱えてしまう
ずっと前にです
Of course,
we shouldn’t expect
もちろん配偶者に
完全さを期待すべきではありません
perfection from our mate,
しかし交際期間中に
物事に取り組むことは—
but working through matters
during courtship
is another opportunity
that Jehovah provides
平和裏に不和を解決するために—
エホバが与えてくださった
一つの機会です
to settle differences in peace.
There’s something common
to every successful marriage
成功したクリスチャン同士の結婚には—
共通点があります
between two Christians.
エホバを第一にし—
It is their putting Jehovah first
神に対する互いの献身を
支持することです
and supporting
each other’s personal dedication to God.
This is certainly true
with Viv and Ann Mouritz,
これはモリッツ夫妻にとっても同様です
serving
in the Australasia branch.
二人はオーストラレーシア支部で
奉仕しています
They’ve been married
for 65 years
二人は結婚して65年になり—
全時間奉仕は合わせて
131年になります
and have
a combined 131 years
in full-time service.
エホバの組織内で何を行なうかを
決定しようとしている—
Listen to their advice
for younger ones
若者へのアドバイスを聞きましょう
deciding what to do
in Jehovah’s organization.
I started pioneering
in November 1948.
わたしは1948年11月に
開拓奉仕を始めました
That’s a while ago now.
ずいぶん前のことです
And that’s what I thought
I would do—pioneer.
開拓者になると決めたんです
So I said, “Well, Jehovah,
if I do what you ask me,
それでこう言いました
“エホバ あなたの
求めていることをします”
“どんな割り当ても受け入れ
どこへでも行きます”
“I accept whatever assignment
you give me,
“and I’ll just go
where you send me,
“割り当ては求めませんが
断わることはしません”
and I won’t seek an assignment,
but I won’t refuse one.”
That’s all I intended to do
as far as I knew,
開拓奉仕以外のことは
考えていませんでしたが—
but then I had only been pioneering
about a year
1年したとき
封筒を受け取りました
when I got this envelope,
and the letter said:
手紙には “同封の用紙に
記入してください”とあり—
“Please fill in the enclosed form.”
It was an application for Bethel,
and I thought,
ベテルの申込書でした
‘Goodness, I didn’t think of Bethel.
“まさか ベテルとは！”と
思いました
I told Jehovah I’d go where he sent me,
so don’t argue, just do it.’
エホバにはどこへでも行くと
述べたので—
とにかくやろうと思いました
I was working in the printery
cleaning out old ink tins
わたしはプリンタリーで奉仕し—
インキの缶を洗ったり
印刷予定を作ったりしました
and making schedules
for printing and so on.
And then I got to work
on the press too,
そしてプレスでも働きました
but I wasn’t there very long
when they moved me to the office.
でも ほどなくして
事務所に割り当てられました
Well, you learn a lot in Bethel.
ベテルでは多くのことを学べます
You learn how to live
with your brothers,
兄弟たちと
うまく生活する方法や—
which you’re not used to.
エホバの組織がどのように機能するかを
学ぶこともできます
You learn about Jehovah’s organization
—you see how it operates.
わたしは経験豊かな兄弟たちと
一緒に奉仕する特権がありました
I had the privilege of working alongside
brothers who had lots of experience.
I got assigned
to Metropolitan Congregation.
わたしはメトロポリタン会衆に
割り当てられ—
そこにアンがいました
That’s where Ann was.
Yeah, we got married
in October 1951,
わたしたちは
1951年10月に結婚し—
and two weeks later,
2週間後に わたしは
開拓奉仕を始めました
I started pioneering.
I was 20 at that time
when we started circuit work,
巡回奉仕を始めた時
わたしは20歳でした
and I’d only pioneered for a year;
わたしは1年しか開拓奉仕を
していませんでしたから—
so of course I was very worried
油そそがれた者たちも含む—
and scared about having to witness
with sisters
長年の開拓者の姉妹たちと
証言することに—
that had pioneered for years
and some of them even of the anointed.
不安を抱いていました
半分泣きながら
メルボルンに行きました
I cried halfway to Melbourne.
兄弟姉妹たち 特に子どもたちと
親しくなれたのは—
We got very close
to the brothers and sisters
and especially to the children,
so we really loved that.
とても楽しかったです
その後 1958年に
ニューヨークでの国際大会に—
And then we
got the opportunity to go
to New York
to the international convention
出席する機会がありました
in 1958.
わたしたちが出席することを
知った協会は—
When the Society found out
we were going, they sent us
ギレアデの申込書を送ってきました
an application for Gilead,
and we thought, ‘Oh, my goodness.
“どうしよう?
やっていけるだろうか？”と思いました
How can we do that?’
でも “いやとは言わない”ことに
していました
So we said,
“Well, we don’t say no.”
大会の後 わたしたちは
カナダに6か月間—
After the ‘58 convention,
we were assigned to special pioneer
特別開拓者として割り当てられました
in Canada for six months.
ノア兄弟はわたしたち
英連邦諸国からの40人を—
Brother Knorr said
we were in cold storage,
so there were about 40 of us
冷凍庫で保存すると言いました
from British Commonwealth countries.
それは楽しい経験でした
So that was a good experience too.
初めて冬を経験しましたが
とにかくやりました
We saw winter for the first time.
I did, anyway.
And we took pictures
of snow and ice and icicles
雪や氷や つららの写真を撮って—
to show in our assignment when we
got into India or Africa or somewhere.
インドやアフリカの割り当ての際に
見せようと思っていました
エホバのユーモアで
フィンランドに割り当てられました
And Jehovah had a sense of humor;
he sent us to Finland.
Well, the schooling you get from Gilead
ギレアデや他の学校の授業は—
or the other schools
エホバの組織—
およびそれがどのように機能するかを
理解する助けとなります
helps you to see Jehovah’s organization
and how it works.
フィンランドについては
あまり知りませんでした
We didn’t know a lot about Finland
except that we knew it was cold
and clean
寒くて きれいで—
オーストラリアからは
遠いことくらいでした
and a long way from Australia.
Being so far from Australia,
オーストラリアからは
遠く離れているので—
家族に会うために
家に帰ることが—
we knew that we
wouldn’t be able to get home
しばらくはできなくなることを
知っていました
to see our families,
not for a long, long time.
When we moved into Finland,
the brothers
フィンランドに移動したとき—
ロシアの兄弟たちは禁令下にいました
in Russia and those countries
were under ban.
必要とされていた霊的な食物を—
They needed spiritual food,
供給しなければなりません
and so it had to be supplied to them.
それで旅行者を送り込み—
So we used to send people in as tourists,
and they would meet
地元の兄弟たちに会って
食物を供給しました
the brothers there
and deliver the food to them.
Without Jehovah’s blessing
and his spirit,
エホバの祝福と聖霊がなければ—
we couldn’t have done it at all.
何一つ行なえませんでした
It’s amazing to think
that the amount of spiritual food
供給された霊的食物の—
量の多さには驚かされます
that got in there,
they translated it,
それらが翻訳され提供されたのです
and they made it available.
こうした事が何の事故もなく—
And we did that for over 20 years
without any mishaps.
20年以上続けられました
It couldn’t happen
without Jehovah’s blessing.
エホバの祝福なしではありえません
Leaving Finland was not easy,
of course.
フィンランドを去るのは
簡単ではありませんでした
We had mixed feelings,
複雑な気持ちでしたが—
but, actually,
I saw Jehovah’s hand
実際には割り当ての上に—
in the assignment
エホバのみ手を感じました
because we really got back
to Australia
それは両親が助けを
必要としていた時に—
at a time when my parents
were needing help,
オーストラリアに戻ったからです
so we didn’t have to leave Bethel
ベテルや全時間奉仕を離れることなく—
or full-time service
to give that help.
援助することができたのです
We were asked
to go to Russia in 1999.
1999年にロシアに行くように言われ—
That turned out
to be two and a half years.
2年半ほどいました
I was a little apprehensive
about going to Russia,
ロシアに行くことは少し不安でしたが—
but it was really one of the most
memorable assignments
これまでに経験した
最も思い出に残る割り当てでした
we’ve ever had.
In Russia, the brothers
were not used to house-to-house work
ロシアではずっと禁令でしたから—
兄弟たちは家から家の奉仕には
慣れていませんでした
because of all the years under ban.
戸口ですぐ会話を始めないので—
And that was quite different
because you go to the door;
家の人は何の用で来たのか
知りたがります
you can’t just strike up a conversation.
The person wants to know
why you are there.
通りで会った人を
再訪問することができません
And you can’t make
a return visit on someone
you met on the street
どこに住んでいるかわからないからです
—well, you don’t know
where he lives.
でも家を訪問するなら
再訪問はできます
If you’ve called at his house, you do,
and you can make a return visit.
The brothers saw
the advantage of that.
兄弟たちはその利点に気づきました
But they had to learn.
It was a new thing.
それは学ぶべき新たな事柄でした
Circuit overseers had to learn
how to visit congregations,
巡回監督は会衆の訪問の仕方を
学ぶ必要がありました
and Polish brothers came in
and helped a lot with that
ポーランドの兄弟たちが
巡回訪問の援助をしましたが—
—did circuit work—
but they too had to learn.
彼らも学はなければなりませんでした
So it was a big change for them
to come from working
under ban all their lives
長年の禁令下での奉仕から—
いまや世界の他の場所と
同じ方法で奉仕することは—
to now working the way
the rest of the world does.
実に大きな変化でした
The best decision I ever made
わたしが下した最善の決定は—
was to put my life
in Jehovah’s hands,
命をエホバのみ手にゆだね—
and to say, “You decide
“行くべき道と
すべきことを決めてください”と—
where I go and what I do.”
エホバに述べたことです
I’ve had the feeling all along,
and it’s proven true so far,
今も同じ気持ちでいます
that everything I have done
自分のしたことすべては—
has been training for something else.
何らかの訓練になってきたと
思っています
So, what I’m doing now
is still training.
今していることも
新しい世のための訓練です
It must be for the new world
because I haven’t got
much time left in this one.
自分にあまり時間がないからです
What will it be?
Well, who knows?
どんな割り当てでしょうか？
楽しみです
お勧めしたいのは
自分で決めないことです
So my recommendation
to everyone is:
Don’t decide for yourself.
エホバに決めてもらうのです
Let Jehovah do it.
モリッツ兄弟姉妹は割り当てに関して—
Brother and Sister Mouritz
always looked to Jehovah
for their assignments.
常にエホバを見ていました
For Brother Mouritz,
that’s meant serving
モリッツ兄弟にとって—
それはフィンランド, インド,
ロシア, ポーランド, ウクライナ—
on the Branch Committees
in Finland, India,
Russia, Poland, Ukraine,
またオーストラレーシアで
支部委員として奉仕し—
and Australasia
and the privilege of making visits
また 本部代表として70以上の国を
訪問する特権を意味したのです
to more than 70 countries
as a representative
of world headquarters.
確かに状況が許すなら—
We can certainly pursue
any form of service
どのような形の奉仕でも
追い求めることができます
that our circumstances allow.
導きを祈り求める際—
But when we pray
for Jehovah’s direction,
わたしたちはエホバの組織と
自分にとって—
we rely on him to send us
最善の益となるところに
遣わしてくだるよう—
where it benefits his organization
エホバに物事をゆだねます
and ourselves the most.
The willing spirit
to do Jehovah’s will
野外での新たな割り当てを受けた
ベテル奉仕者たちは—
is shared by Bethelites
who have received
エホバのご意志を喜んで
行なう精神を示しています
new assignments in the field.
Adjustments in the work at Bethel
ベテルでの仕事の調整は
宣べ伝える業の重要性を示しています
have put greater emphasis
on the preaching work.
More resources,
経験ある聖書の教え手を含む—
including experienced Bible teachers,
さらに多くの資産が忙しい収穫の業に
振り向けられています
are being directed
to the busy harvest.
In this report
from the South Africa branch,
南アフリカ支部からの報告では—
神権的な指示に従う忠節な人々の声を
聞くことができます
we hear from loyal ones
who are supporting theocratic direction.
On September 23, 2015,
it was announced
2015年9月23日
統治体はすべての支部で—
at all branches that
the Governing Body was requesting
ベテル家族の規模が縮小される
という発表を行ないました
all Bethel families to reduce in size.
For me personally,
自分としては9月23日水曜日の
その発表はわくわくさせるものでした
when they made that announcement
on Wednesday, September 23,
that was exciting.
It was—
とても重要な発表だと分かりました
I knew it was momentous.
When the announcement was made,
その発表で終わりが
いかに近づいているかが分かり—
tears welled up in my eyes
because I realized how close we are
目に涙があふれました
to the end.
目をつむり “なんでも行ないます”と
エホバに言いました
And I remember just closing my eyes
and saying to Jehovah,
“Whatever you want, we’ll do.”
When I received news of my reassignment,
割り当て変更の知らせを受け取った
当初は ぼう然としていました
initially I was numb.
When I got the news
割り当て変更の知らせを受けた時
はじめはとても不安な気持ちでした
about my reassignment,
I was so scared in the beginning.
It caught me off guard.
わたしは自分にはあまり
関係ないと思っていました
I wasn’t expecting it.
We were quite shocked and sad,
かなりショックでしたし
悲しくなりましたが—
but we were encouraged by the brothers
ベテルや会衆の兄弟たちに
励まされました
at Bethel and also in the congregation.
The direction from the Governing Body
統治体の指示は—
was that we were being reassigned
わたしたちが正規開拓者としての
割り当てを受けることでした
as regular pioneers.
We signed the forms for pioneering
that very Thursday.
木曜日には開拓者の
申し込み書に記入しました
For me, I’ve always appreciated
the scripture at 1 Samuel 12:22
サムエル第一 12章22節には—
“エホバはその偉大な
み名のために—”
where it states there:
“For the sake of his great name,
“ご自分の民を捨て去ることは
されない”とあります
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
I don’t want to forget my Bethel time,
ベテルのことは決して忘れません
素晴らしいものでした
because it was lovely,
でも開拓奉仕に集中して
楽しみたいと思います
but I want to stretch forward ahead
to pioneering and really enjoy it.
We prayed specifically for a place
特に祈り求めたのは
宣教に注意を集中するために—
that is going to help us
to be as simple
できるだけ簡素な生活ができるような
場所を見いだすということでした
as possible so that we can focus
our attention to the ministry.
All that I’d love to say
to everyone who has been reassigned
割り当ての変更を受けた皆さん
すべてにお伝えしたいことは—
is that Jehovah is our Father,
エホバはわたしたちの父であり
その責任を放棄することは—
and he will never relinquish
his responsibility as a Father.
決してないということです
He will take care of us.
世話してくださいます
We are losing four couples
4組の夫婦が会衆からいなくなります
from our congregation.
And I would like to tell
割り当てられた会衆には
彼らが真の霊的な人で—
the congregations
where they have been assigned to
新たな会衆にとって
貴重な資産になる人々であることを—
that they are getting
real spiritual people
and that they are
really going to be an asset
伝えたいと思います
to their congregation.
I just want to also thank
会衆の兄弟たちに
感謝したいと思います
the brothers in the congregation
where we are going to
because they organized
secular work for us
世俗の仕事や ボニーが述べたように
宿舎も見つけてくれたのです
and also, as Bonnie mentioned,
accommodation.
So they made it easier for us
おかげで割り当てが
とても楽しみになりました
to look forward to our assignment.
もちろん これがエホバから
来ていることを知っています
But we know this,
of course, comes from Jehovah.
And so the Branch Committee said,
支部委員会は“この件はすぐに
進める必要がある”と言いました
“Well, we have to move quickly with this.”
We asked the family,
わたしたちは “物事を決めるために
2-3週間の猶予”を—
“Please, give us two,
three weeks to work things out,”
and that is what they appreciated.
ベテル家族に求めました
Congregations phoned in.
諸会衆に電話で連絡が取られ—
The Bethelites were offered jobs.
ベテル家族には仕事や
宿舎が提供されました
They were offered accommodation.
Our congregation is delighted
二人の若いベテル奉仕者が
来てくれたので会衆は喜びました
having two young Bethelites
coming and joining us.
Our congregation
has quite a number of young people.
会衆にはかなりの数の若者がいます
若者たちは二人からすでに
たくさんの益を受けています
We can already see that
it’s going to benefit them quite a lot.
We’ve actually assisted them
二人のために住む場所を
見つけたり—
in getting a place
where they could stay,
会衆の一員として腰を据えて
活動したりできるよう援助しました
and also we’ve assisted them
to settle in
and be part of the congregation.
Welcome to our new home!
わが家へようこそ
移動して1週間です
We’ve been here
a little over a week now.
The brothers helped
to paint the house,
兄弟たちが家のペンキ塗り タイル張り
掃除などを手伝ってくれました
to put tiles on,
to clean the entire place.
本当にたくさんのことを
してくださいました
So they really did
a lot of work in our behalf.
Also, memories
of our friends from Bethel.
これはベテルの思い出です
It was about six months ago
6か月前には開拓者学校を楽しみました
when we enjoyed pioneer school.
Thanks to our brothers,
we were able to find employment.
兄弟たちのおかげで
仕事が見つかりました
エホバはずっと祈りに答えてくださり—
Jehovah has been
answering our prayers,
and sometimes
he has been answering
時には祈る前からわたしたちの
不安に答えてくださいました
our concerns
even before we even pray about it.
No doubt,
南アフリカにおける
この感動的な経験は—
these extraordinary experiences
in South Africa
世界中で見られています
are mirrored all over the world.
わたしたちの示す互いへの愛は—
The love we show
to each other is a reflection
わたしたちに対する
エホバの偉大な愛の反映です
of Jehovah’s great love
for each of us,
and we thank him to be a part
このすばらしい兄弟関係を
エホバに感謝します
of this amazing brotherhood.
統治体は神権的な指示に—
The Governing Body
deeply appreciates
忠節に答え応じる兄弟たちに
深く感謝しています
the brotherhood’s loyal response
to theocratic direction.
Change is not always easy,
変化は常に簡単では
ありませんが—
but it helps when we look
at Jehovah’s blessing
新たな霊的備えや
業の調整の上にある—
on new spiritual provisions
エホバの祝福を見るなら
助けが得られます
and adjustments to the work.
Letters of appreciation
from our brothers
兄弟たちからの感謝の手紙によって—
add to the Governing Body’s confidence
統治体はエホバが組織を導いておられる
との確信を増し加えています
that Jehovah
is directing his organization.
A sister from the United States
wrote this about JW Broadcasting,
アメリカの一姉妹はJW Broadcasting
についてこう書きました
“Often the programming seems like
“プログラムはよく祈りに対する
直接の答えのように感じます”
a direct answer to a prayer.”
After a particularly difficult day,
she added:
特に大変だった一日のあと
こう言っています
“What did I find today at home
for me like a present from Jehovah?
“エホバからの贈り物として
今日家で何を見つけたと思いますか？”
The March [2016] broadcast
. . . dealing with discouragement.”
“落胆に対処する方法を扱った
3月のブロードキャスティングです”
After watching
the January 2016 broadcast,
2016年1月のブロード
キャスティングを見た後—
オーストリアの一家族はこう書きました
a family from Austria wrote:
‘Our eldest son is serving
in the branch in Selters, Germany.
“長男はドイツのゼルターズの
支部で奉仕しています”
‘We are very proud of him,
but we terribly miss him.
“自慢の息子ですが
とても寂しく感じています”
‘So we love the new song,
“I Give You My Best.”
“ですから「わたしの宝を」
という歌が大好きです”
‘It’s heartwarming
that you know our feelings
“わたしたちの気持ちや犠牲を
理解してくださり うれしくなります”
and value our offers.’
Jehovah is certainly giving us
エホバは確かに必要とするものを
必要な時に与えくださいます
what we need
when we need it.
And it comes to us
in such variety.
しかも あらゆる種類のものをです
This next music video,
for example,
例えばこのミュージック・ビデオは—
不和を解決するという論題に
ふさわしいものでしょう
fits well with our discussion
on settling differences.
It begins with a situation
between a young mother
若い母親とその姑の状況が
最初に出てきますが—
and her mother-in-law
and reminds us
“互いに許し合う”ことを
思い起こさせてくれます
to “Forgive One Another.”
あなたは 親切で
Yes, you had the best of intentions.
Kindnesses too numerous to mention.
いつもよく気がつくの
でも心が壊れそう
But thoughtless words
just cut me to the heart.
気持ちすれ違い
Then, as a tear appears, I see.
Things aren’t what they seem to be.
涙こぼれる
陽が沈む前に
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
目と目合わせながら
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
心に寄り添えば　見える
あなたの 優しさ
Sisters today, sisters we’ll stay.
時にはぶつかり合い
Getting along is not always easy.
Angry words can bring you down, believe me.
君の良さ　見えなくて
Then you find a reason to forgive,
And now you realize it’s true;
でも信じていたい
僕たちはきっと
同じ思いさ
Letting go’s the thing to do.
陽が沈む前に
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
友の声 探して
傷ついた心 振り捨て
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
ふたりの 明日を見る
Brothers today, brothers we’ll stay.
Not one thing said or done can break us up.
Love’s a bond of unity.
愛の絆
簡単には ほどけない
Cancel the debt; forgive and forget.
That’s the way true friendship should be.
許すたび 強くなる
もう 振り返らない
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
陽が沈む前に
目と目合わせながら
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
心に寄り添えば 見える
Here in our hearts, that’s where it starts.
静かに 動き出す
奏でる 愛のハーモニー
Bonded in love, forgiving one another.
Did you see two critical areas
許す必要のある二つの重大な分野に
気付きましたか？
where we need to be forgiving?
It was in the family
and in the congregation.
家族と会衆という分野です
We’ll always have reasons
この不完全な世にあっては
いつでも許すべき理由があります
in this imperfect world
to forgive.
Look for the opportunities
in your life
エホバに見倣い 人を許す機会を
生活の中で求めてください
to imitate Jehovah
and forgive others.
As we conclude our program,
結びに ニューヨーク ウォーウィック
にある世界本部を訪問しましょう
we take you on a visit
to world headquarters
in Warwick, New York.
ベテル家族はこの新しい
仕事場へと移動しています
The Bethel family
has been moving
into their new work areas.
2万5千人以上の兄弟姉妹たちが
この施設の建設で働きました
More than 25,000 brothers
and sisters
worked on the construction
of the facility.
これはテンポラリー・ボランティア—
It was a united effort
by temporary volunteers,
建設サーバント ベテル奉仕者
建設グループ そして—
construction servants,
Bethelites, construction groups,
これまでの王国会館プロジェクトで
働いたボランティアの—
and volunteers
who previously worked
結集した努力の賜物です
on Kingdom Hall projects.
今年の初め—
Earlier this year,
workers were making
世界本部の奉仕者の到着に備えて
最終的な準備が行なわれました
final preparations for the arrival
of world headquarters staff.
見学が始まると 訪問者たちは—
When open for tours,
visitors will enjoy
聖書の歴史的展示物
視覚に訴えるエホバの証人の歴史—
the historic Bible display,
a visual history exhibit
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
またエホバが組織を今日どのように
導いておられるかを説明した—
and an interactive museum
参加型のミュージアムを楽しめます
explaining how Jehovah directs
his organization today.
世界本部の完成を助けてくださった
皆さんのことをエホバに感謝します
We thank Jehovah for all
who helped to complete
the new world headquarters.
それには幾千人ものボランティア—
That includes
the thousands of volunteers
また定期的な寄付を通して
世界的な業を支えてくださった—
but also the millions
of you dear brothers and sisters
兄弟姉妹たちも含まれています
who support the worldwide work
皆さんに愛をお送りし—
with your regular donations.
エホバが一致した兄弟関係を
祝福してくださるよう祈ります
We send you our love
and pray for Jehovah
to bless
our united brotherhood.
ニューヨーク市ブルックリンから
JW Broadcastingでした!
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting!